Guide to the Leonid Yakobson collection M2081
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Leonid Yakobson collection
1941-2012
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Ross, Janice
I포Akobson, Leonid
M2081
5 Linear Feet
13 box(es) (12 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box)
A collection of photographs, videos, and research files related to the Russian choreographer Leonid Yakobson (1904-1975).
Scope and Contents
A collection of photographs, videos, and research files related to the Russian ballet dancer and choreographer Leonid Yakobson (1904-1975), donated by Stanford dance professor Janice Ross, who used this material to write a monograph on Yakobson: "Like a Bomb Going Off: Leonid Yakobson and Ballet as Resistance in Soviet Russia."
Most of the collection is annotated with notes and identification in Russian, some of which is translated into English. There are also notes from Ross as she organized her files. Many of the photographs are reprinted in the book. Yakobson's wife Irina, who taught at the San Francisco Ballet School in the 1980s and 90s, provided Ross with much of this collection. Other sources include former dancers and Russian archives.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Choreographers -- Soviet Union; Ballet -- Soviet Union -- History; Ross, Janice; I포Akobson, Leonid; I포Akobson, Leonid; I포Akobson, Irina Davydovna
- Series 1. Videotapes- Performances
  Scope and Contents
  52 numbered videocassettes in both American (NTSC) and European formats (PAL, MESECAM). There are two commercially produced tapes; the remainder are dubs. Many have notes in Russian (and some English) on their cases or enclosed. The majority of videos feature live performances of ballet works. A listing of the videotapes is available: to request a copy contact Special Collections at specialcollections@stanford.edu. This listing is also in a folder in Box 1.
  - 1-13 (Box 1)
  - 14-26 (Box 2)
  - 27-39 (Box 3)
  - 40-52 (Box 4)
- Series 2. Photographs- Performances
  These photographs date from the early 1940s to the mid-1980s, and include original prints, copy prints, contact sheets, and negatives.
  - Shurale, 1941 (Box 5, Folders 1-2)
  - The Blind Girl, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Pulcinella, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Gossips, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Vienna Waltz, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Vagrant, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Spartacus, 1956 (Box 5, Folders 8-9)
  - 햃 Couple in Love, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Twelve, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Land of Miracles, 1967 (Box 5, Folders 12-13)
  - Vestris, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Exercise XX, 1971 (Box 5, Folders 15-16)
  - Contrasts, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Travelling Circus, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Jewish Wedding (Wedding Cort칟ge), 1971 (Box 5, Folders 19-20, Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Rodin Sculptures, 1971 (Box 6, Folders 2-8)
  - Classicism-Romanticism, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Russian Miniatures / Snow Maiden, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - The City, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Symphony of Eternity, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Baba-Yaga, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Brilliant Divertissement, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Mozartiana, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Six Pas de deux, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Extase, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - The Cowboys, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Hiroshima, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - The Bedbug, 1974 (Box 7, Folders 1-2, Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Distraught Dictator, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Unknown ballets (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Series 3. Photographs- Yakobson
  - Rehearsals (Box 7, Folders 4-10)
  - Bows & finales (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - With colleagues (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Portraits (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Travel, Family (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - With Irina, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Grave monument (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Negatives (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Photocopied photographs (Box 8, Folders 5-6)
  - Tif files on CD-R (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - New prints (Box 11, Folders 1-3)
  - Negatives (Box 11, Folders 4-6)
  - Rehearsal photos by Anatoly Pronin (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Series 4. Janice Ross book, etc.
  Material assembled by Ross for her book "Like a Bomb Going Off." The majority are secondary sources sent by various people, including members of the Yakobson family. Many documents are in Russian, and some have been partially or fully translated into English. These were unfoldered for the most part, and the original order has been retained (i.e. mailers and envelopes with their contents). There are two folders of scans and photocopies of Yakobson correspondence, many articles about him, and a listing of his library. Also included are transcripts of Ross's original interviews.
  - Research material, notes, etc. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Research material (Box 12, Box 13)
  - Book draft typescript (Box 9, Folders 1-2)
  - Stanford dance class, etc. (Box 8, Folder 9)